A Finding Aid to the Siri Berg Papers, 1966-1998, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Siri Berg papers
1966-1998
Archives of American Art
Berg, Siri, 1921-2020
AAA.bergsiri
Archival Resource Key
1.1 Linear feet
The papers of Swedish-born painter and collagist Siri Berg measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1966 to 1998. The bulk of the collection consists of studies for artwork, and may include paint color choices and samples, sketches, plans, and notes. Also found are scattered correspondence, photographs, printed material, and a video recording of Berg in her SoHo studio.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center.
Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
The papers of Swedish-born painter and collagist Siri Berg measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1966 to 1998. The bulk of the collection consists of studies for artwork, and may include paint color choices and samples, sketches, plans, and notes. Also found are scattered correspondence, photographs, printed material, and a video recording of Berg in her SoHo studio.
Studies for artworks include Berg's The Black Series, Cosmic Veil, Kabala Series, La Ronde, and Tops of Kites. Photographs depict Berg, exhibitions, and works of art.
Biographical / Historical
Siri Berg (1921-2020) was a collagist, abstract painter, and educator active in New York City, who was known for making collages of geometric shapes on paper she printed herself.
Berg was born in Stockholm, Sweden, and studied art in Brussels, Belgium, before immigrating to the United States in 1940. Berg began her career working in window design for the New York City fashion industry. Later, in the 1970s, Berg began to focus on commissioned work and moved to a studio in SoHo. She exhibited her works throughout New York City and Philadelphia and was an active member of the American Abstract Artists group. Berg was also an educator who taught color theory at Parsons School of Design for over 25 years.
Berg died in New York City in 2020.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Siri Berg donated her papers to the Archives of American Art in 1998.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Painters -- New York (State) -- New York; Educators -- New York (State) -- New York; Women artists; Women painters; Women educators; Video recordings; Collagists -- New York (State) -- New York; American Abstract Artists
- Siri Berg Papers, 1966-1998; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, OV 4
  Scope and Contents
  Art study files may include color samples, color tests, notes, plans, and sketches. Correspondents include Centre Georges Pompidou, Peje Emilsson, Guggenheim Museum, Israel Museum, Jerusalem, and the University of Alabama at Birmingham. Photographs depict Berg, her exhibitions, and artworks. Printed materials consist of clippings, exhibition announcements, and catalogs. Also found is a video recording of Berg in her SoHo studio.
  - Art Study, The Black Series, 1976-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Art Study, Collograph, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Study, Cosmic Veils, Prints 439-441, 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Art Study, Cycle of 5, 1973-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Art Study, Environmental Boxes, 1979-1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Art Study, Four Elements, 1978-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Art Study, Four Faculties, 1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Art Study, Kabala Series, 1975-1986; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8-12)
  - Art Study, Kinneret, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Art Study, Kaleidoscope Story, Oversized, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
  - Art Study, La Ronde, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Art Study, La Ronde, 1972-1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - Art Study, La Ronde, Oversized, 1972-1984; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
  - Art Study, Patterns, 421-4288, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Art Study, Prints, 390-393, 396, 1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Art Study, Through a Looking Glass Series, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Art Study, Tops of Kites 610-613, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Art Study, Triangle Black and White, 1977; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Art Study, The White Series, 1977-1978; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Art Study, Works on Paper, 1974-1975; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Art Study, General, Oversized, circa 1975; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 4)
  - Commissions, Notes, 1977-1979; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1975-1998; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Photographs, 1966-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Printed Material, 1990-1997; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Siri Berg in SoHo Studio, circa 1990; Archival Resource Key; 1 Videocassette (Box 3, Folder 1)